[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net
sc radio is brought to you by the ieee
computer society by ieee software
magazine
online at computer.org software
developers got some extra time on your
hands
use it to learn a new database enter
systems iris allows you to choose your
language tools and environment
so you can collaborate build faster and
deploy more efficiently
now's your chance to try out inner
systems iris the fastest way to build
applications
ready set code
visit intersystems.com try iris to learn
more
for software engineering radio this is
akshay manchali today we have jake reps
and we're going to talk about k-sequel
db
jay is the ceo and co-founder of
confluent prior to confluent he was the
lead architect for data and
infrastructure at linkedin
he is the initial developer of several
open source projects including apache
kafka
jay was previously a guest on sc radio
on episode 162 and more recently on
episode
393 jay welcome back to the show thanks
so much for having me
so before we get into k sql db let's
talk about a few basics let's start with
kafka
what is kafka yeah that's that's a good
question so we we we call it
uh an event streaming platform but that
kind of begs the question of what what
the heck is uh
event streaming and and so you know it
really is kind of a new category of
thing that's come around
some people compare it to being a bit
like a kind of message queue
that that you send messages to and it
kind of queues them up and sends them
out but it's a bit
it's a bit more than that so the idea is
you know kafka acts as a kind of
distributed cluster
and you can read and write streams of
events and by events i mean
you say something happened and it gets
recorded
as a kind of linear stream almost like a
array
of these events it just keeps growing
and growing and the rights all go to the
end of the array
and readers can can read along in that
stream
and so you know those those events could
be anything they could be things
happening in the business it could be
you know sales that are occurring uh you
know messages of all kinds
you know so this is a very new thing
kafka itself has become quite popular
now so it's
you know it's out in the world you know
really at large scale we're doing our
kafka summit uh this year and you know
it looks like we'll have over 25 000
people who are
signed up and and gonna attend that uh
virtually
so so you know it's really become a
popular
um layer for building these kind of
asynchronous event-driven microservices
that communicate
through these events it's become popular
for building
you know real-time low-latency pipelines
for data that
you know stream things into a different
data systems or
sas layers or apis and and it's become
you know kind of part of the
the modern stack in in a lot of ways
and so so that that's kind of the basic
concept you know you can interact with
kafka through a couple different
apis there's these lower level apis
where you would
produce or write data into one of these
streams
there's a consumer api where you would
you know read
or subscribe to data that's being
written and
then then there's apis which allow you
to use pre-built connectors
that hook up and maybe capture changes
occurring in a database or publish
changes out into some data store or sas
application and there's hundreds of
these pre-built connectors for different
types of system and applications you can
kind of hook them up and turn their data
into streams or take streams in kafka
and
you know send it off to other other
systems
and yeah then there's a stream
processing apis
in kafka which allow you to take these
streams of data and react
or respond or process them as they occur
so you could imagine
you know maybe you have a stream of the
sales that are occurring in some
e-commerce application and you can
imagine you know
triggering order fulfillment or counting
how many sales you had by
geographical region as as the sales
occurred
and so those are the different ways of
interacting with these streams of data
and so that's you know that's kind of
the the 30 second in a nutshell
explanation of
of what kafka is great so i keep hearing
things like uh kafka topics so what's a
kafka topic
yeah yeah so you know topic is kind of a
terminology we borrowed from the
messaging world
it's really just the name for one of
these data streams
so you know maybe i would have in this
ecommerce application i might have a
sales
topic and there might be many ways that
a sale occurs right maybe it occurs on
an iphone app
or it occurs you know through some
back-end system or it occurs
i don't know and you can imagine each of
those sales being
published out to this topic which means
really just appended to that
kind of infinitely growing array that i
described
and that might trigger all kinds of
activity on the back end
so there might be a system that does
order fulfillment
and every time a new sale is published
it would react and whatever
you know is needed to send the
information off to a warehouse and get
that thing into a box and get it sent
off that it would be responsible for
that maybe there's something that
updates the information uh for customers
maybe there's something that
updates uh you know the kind of coupons
and whatever and
you know sets up the returns whatever
whatever it is that you would do maybe
there's analytical systems that provide
reporting
that would need to update they would all
subscribe to that feed
of sales and react to it and so the name
for that
feed or stream is a topic in in kafka
terminology
interesting so what's different about
kafka compared to a message broker
that moves data from a publisher to a
subscriber
yeah that's that's a great question so
you know we when we were building in
this area
that there were a whole set of different
kind of cues and messaging layers
you know the kind of foundational
technology differences in kafka
that make it a little different i'll
describe and then i'll describe kind of
like from the user's point of view what
do you get it's different
so as a technology layer what's really
different is you know kafka is
storing persistent replicated uh events
or messages right
and it can store them really for any
amount of time and you can hold lots of
them
and that means everything is kind of
multi-subscriber
like any of these topics it can have
zero subscribers or consumers it could
have
dozens hundreds of subscribers or
consumers and
so you know this the this idea of really
orienting around
events being uh always multi-subscriber
being persistent
and then building around kind of a
modern distributed system that allows
this to
scale out horizontally and do so
you know more elastically and
dynamically all that's
that's fairly different from a
traditional message queue which is more
oriented around
you know individual servers that would
hold messages where they would put them
on disk only
if needed and you know beyond that you
know kafka doesn't really provide a cue
abstraction when you read a message it
doesn't
you know pop it off the queue instead it
has this kind of stream
and it turns out that this is
you know those qualities end up really
important
if you're trying to build a reliable
data pipeline that guarantees the
delivery
it turns out it's really important if
you're trying to hook up multiple
applications or systems within a company
and guarantee that they all get it
it's operationally very important just
because you don't want something where
if the memory
fills up and it goes to disk it suddenly
gets 10 times slower and tips over
and for all those reasons i think you
know kafka has ended up being a much
better
platform for large-scale usage within a
company and then it also turns out and
this was
you know part of our motivation that
this abstraction is a much
better foundation for stream processing
for working with this data
in real time so if you think about it
the message queues
it's a pretty low level abstraction you
can kind of put a message in the queue
you can take it out
but everything beyond that is kind of up
to you to go figure out in your code
and a lot of things we do with data
there actually are common patterns and
that's why databases
you know they don't just have put and
get they have also a bunch of
functionality that allows you to compute
things off of the data
and that's you know i'm sure we'll get
into that when we talk about k sequel db
and stream processing
you know it's very very hard to build
that on top of a traditional queue
and and kafka was really designed with
that in mind actually we started with
the idea of
hey it would make sense to do a lot more
real-time processing on data
how would we do that and then we
realized well the first thing you need
if you want
you know stream processing is you need
streams and you need them at scale
across the company and that that was
actually what motivated a lot of the
early kafka development
with that information let's jump into k
sql db which is our main topic
so what is k sequel db yeah that's
that's a great question so
i started to touch on stream processing
and you know this you know it's probably
worth just describing what i mean by
that
and you know what the difference is from
batch processing or
more traditional databases so you know
i'll explain it by analogy you know the
way databases typically work is they
have
kind of a pile of data whenever you run
a query
they actually need the data to be static
and unchanging
and the query is is just kind of at a
point in time and so database would
usually
lock that table or have some kind of
concurrency mechanism to get a view on
that that doesn't change
it would scan over it and compute the
results of your query and it would give
it back
and so you know the assumption is that
query is just a very transient thing
and it gives you an answer at a point in
time of course that that answer is
potentially immediately out of date it
doesn't get updated but
but that actually makes sense if you're
if you're building a ui driven
application you kind of want
to know the answer as of right now
you're not really you don't really care
what the answer is in the future in a
lot of cases
although even ui is is changing a lot as
we have these more dynamic uis that
you know get push updates sent to them
and so but that that's the traditional
model
for databases and so the analogy i think
that makes it easiest to understand
stream processing is you know in the us
they have a census that they do every 10
years
and the way the census works is they
send these people out with
binders and they they go door-to-door
and they
record everybody's name and address and
that's their way of counting how many
people there are
and you can think of that as a kind of
batch process right it's scanning
all the data and it's saying okay here's
a person here's another person here's
another person
and then when you want to get an update
on that you have to kind of go back
and you got to scan all the data again
and um so if you
you know if you explain that to a
software engineer they're like hey
that's kind of funny
you know i don't know if i would build
it that way you know probably what i
would do
is i would record all the births and the
deaths
and if you had that stream of births and
deaths you could keep
kind of a running count of how many
people there were right
and um that's exactly what stream
processing is so the births and destros
or events right those are
big events in in people's lives you can
imagine having attached
all the information about the person who
was born or who died right so
everything you would want to know in a
census their gender
ethnicity whatever and then you could
imagine keeping a kind of running count
on top of that that would say okay
you know now in mountain view california
we have 75
692 people you know a baby is born
uh now it's uh 75 693 right so
so that's that's the fundamental idea
behind stream processing and
you can think of it another way which is
just if you have this kafka cluster and
it has all these real-time streams of
data you want to do things with that
you want to harness those calculate
things take one stream of data translate
it into something else
and stream processing is kind of how you
do that and so you know kafka has a set
of lower level apis that help
to do this they help you to do real-time
aggregation a kind of continuous running
count on data they help you to do joints
so in our e-commerce example maybe you
have this stream of sales
but you also have information about the
customer and you need to put those
together
for fulfillment person purposes okay
this sold but where do i ship it well i
need the address i got to join on
the information about the customer maybe
you're just doing simple filtering maybe
you're looking for the sales that are
above a certain amount
all the kinds of things you might do in
a database so there's there's kind of
low-level capabilities for doing that
in kafka and so what what is k sqldb
well that's really our attempt to bring
this out in a more database
like format so in a database
you can run sql queries and
you know a lot of us know sql it's it's
a it's not a perfect language but it's
an easy language it gives a lot of the
expressive activity of what people want
to do with data
and and you wouldn't you wouldn't
necessarily know if it was applicable to
this kind of stream processing
but it turns out it is it turns out it's
actually a great way of doing real-time
processing
and what we're trying to do in k-sql db
is really
in some sense bring together what we
think are the two sides of databases
one of these sides is really well
developed which is if you have a pile of
data
can you do lookups and queries on top of
it
and in fact that's kind of the only
thing we know in databases
but the other side is if you have a flow
of data can you calculate and update
things off of that
and that's always been a little
underdeveloped in databases they have
some features like
triggers or materialized views that are
you know kind of
very simplistic but it's not actually
you know expressed
uh with the full power of sql on those
streams and so
an example of this would be in a data
warehouse you know once you get all your
data in the data warehouse
the data warehouse gives you all this
wonderful quarry functionality to do
aggregations and lookups and things on
top of it
how you get the data in and how you get
it into the right format
is a little bit of a dark art right like
there's usually some hacked systems that
shove things in then you kind of load
you know run some big batch processes on
top of it
but you can imagine a different world
which is you know the data in the data
warehouse is always up to date
there's queries that run on that data as
it flows in
and there's queries that do lookups to
run reports and so on
and that kind of illustrates i think the
two sides
of this query dynamic the you know
changing data as it flows and
and looking up data as it's as it sits
and in k-sql db those are represented
with two concepts
um streams and tables and you can query
both of them
and you know stream is this kind of
continual
set of changes you know kafka topic and
tables
are aggregates we've calculated right or
you know
lookups it's something that's keyed
right so you might have a table that's
all your customers
by some primary id you know id and you
might have a stream of all the sales
that occurred in a data warehouse they
would call these
facts and dimensions they have this idea
of facts which is basically kind of
events
although you can't really subscribe to
them and they have dimensions which is
the kind of store data about customers
and products and so on
so those are the concepts and then you
know we we support this by having
the idea of push queries and an idea of
pull queries
so the kind of traditional query where
you go do a quick look up that's a pull
query you're kind of pulling the data
out
and the other kind of query is a push
query it runs as the data kind of pushes
in
uh to the system and by putting those
together
it's actually really powerful you can
imagine use cases where you're
kind of building some cache maybe you're
taking feeds of data out of different
data systems and putting together
some aggregate view of your customer or
some pre-materialized
view of data that you need to to serve
some use case
and that that view gets updated every
time the underlying data changes
and then you can do lookups against it
to get a particular row or value
does that make sense yeah so when you
say a pull query
when i do the same thing on a
traditional database
is that the same as a pull query when i
say select star from table is that what
a pool query is and k sequel db yeah
that's right that's right
yeah that's right and so so the
difference now um with this kind of
streaming query is that you can now have
subscriptions that continue to update
as the underlying data changes so so uh
you know traditional query is kind of a
point in time thing like hey what's the
value right now
but you could imagine for systems that
are actually subscribing
you need not just the point in time but
also the ability to get all the changes
and so you might say hey give me the
count of
the number of people in every city but
instead of just getting it right now and
having it be out of date
you would get it have it update as
people moved between cities or as
as people were born or died and that's
that's basically the idea of extending
databases for stream processing for for
events and
streams so in that example let's say i
have a dashboard that is displaying the
running count of people
it's just a single query that i write
and the changes are just automatically
coming into the client
with a push query is that sort of the
idea there yeah that's that's the basic
idea is it is that you can
you know both get a point in time look
up as well as you know continually
continually subscribe and calculate
changes
so what's a table in k sql db is that
traditionally the same as what a
relational database looks like
does it have a schema and types and all
of that
yeah that's right so so the the type
system and the sql is
is very similar to what you would expect
in a traditional database it's just that
now
when in addition to saying create table
you know with the appropriate attributes
you can also say create stream
and you can think of a stream as being
like a kind of table of
immutable data that that has a strong
ordering that's that's only appended to
over time
you know effectively it's like a fact
table in a data warehouse
and and you know a a table in case sqld
is very much like a table in
postgres you know it's something it
typically has some kind of primary key
and you would insert into it or
or change it or look up from it or
modify it in a continuous way
and the key thing that k sql db allows
is for you to go back and forth from
streams to tables
so in that example i gave of e-commerce
you could imagine having this stream of
all the sales that are occurring
you could compute off of that you know
you could take that and you could take
maybe also the
the stream of shipments of products that
are happening and using those two you
could compute
what's my inventory on hand and so the
stream of shipments that's like an event
right uh this
this was shipped this arrived a stream
of sales was like
also events this sold but inventory is
actually a table it's like for each
product
how many of these do we have on hand in
each location and it's going up and down
as those shipments are occurring and and
so you know
the cool thing about this is it allows
you to go back and forth between these
this idea of streams and this idea of
tables
and i think it's actually a very
powerful generalization
of data databases and and how we work
with data
that really has a lot of applications
you know we see the use cases being
this kind of streaming data pipelines
like real pipelines where you're
you know capturing data from different
systems and transforming it
as well as like materializing these
caches use cases around
security where you're looking for the
bad patterns but but it's actually quite
applicable
you know across a lot of different use
cases and systems
so what is the source for k-sql db data
is it a consumer from a kafka topic
yeah k-sql db always works on top of
kafka
but it actually allows you to control
the kafka connectors as well so i
mentioned
kafka has this connect api and the
connect api is a way of building these
simple
plugins that either capture a stream of
data from a system
so there's plugins for mysql or postgres
or oracle there's plugins for different
messaging layers there's plugins for a
lot of
cloud data systems there's plugins for
different sas apis
so it can either capture a stream or it
can take a stream that's in kafka and
publish it out to some system so you can
imagine
you know maybe you have a mysql database
and you're capturing all the changes
coming in from that database and you're
publishing it out
to kafka or you could imagine taking a
stream from kafka
and loading it up into the mysql
database so
so there's connectors usually in both
directions we call them
sources and sinks and so um you know to
make these kind of pipelines
easy k sql db also allows you to control
those connectors
so you can actually have a pretty
end-to-end flow
for for streaming data where you say
okay you know connect to this database
capture all the changes connect to this
database capture all the changes
take those streams combine them in this
way you know materialize this new table
of of data that is being computed off
that and now
do lookups against that and and so it is
actually kind of an end-to-end solution
in this event streaming space whereas
you know really before this i i feel
like people had to piece together
a bunch of different things uh to get
something you know there was
some stream processing which would do
the transformation there was
you know kafka there was integrations
with different systems and then there's
some database you would do the lookups
against
you had to kind of wire all that
together and figure out how to secure it
and so on and so this
this makes it a little bit simpler in
that you really just have
kafka in case equal db to work with and
they're kind of built to work together
and have a same
you know a similar set of abstractions
and
security features and and so on so when
you are ingesting data into k-sql db
can you have some sort of transformation
from the source before you ingest it or
is it a one is to one
data with respect to what's in the kafka
topic that you can just query
differently what's the difference there
yeah you know typically people don't do
a ton of transformation as part of that
load
you know you would you typically do it
afterwards in in uh
k sql but but yeah we do support you
know we call them single message
transforms that
allow you to you know do simplistic you
know munching on a single row as it
comes in
that ends up being important in some
cases there's some sensitive data you
don't want to load or you want to
opt-fusegate or you want to encrypt in a
particular way
kind of on the way in without it ever
being stored in the original form
so you can query quick q sqldb like sql
but is there any difference between
uh just regular sql and k sequel yeah
it's
you know the pull queries are certainly
more limited so you know at the moment
it's limited to
you know um relatively simple lookups
we're working on broadening that further
over time you can imagine you know our
goal isn't to really replace
all databases with this it really is for
use cases around
event streams where you would otherwise
be gluing together multiple technologies
so if
you have a ui driven app that's using
postgres we wouldn't come in and say oh
you know stop that
and use this k sql db thing it really
isn't the case where you're trying to do
things
with streams of data around kafka where
this can suddenly add a lot of
simplicity what would have been a bunch
of custom code and
integration between multiple systems can
do that so so yeah we
we are broadening the query features
over time that do
pull queries but but obviously if all
you're ever doing is pull queries
there's 101 databases to do that the the
magic here really is the the push
queries the kind of stream processing
side of the equation which
is a feature which really hasn't existed
elsewhere
right now there's no better time to
learn a new database
with inner systems irs you can build the
applications you want
however you want them you can connect
your systems
use any data model and apply machine
learning
so you can build data intensive and
mission critical applications in no time
level up your skills with inner systems
iris the fastest way to build
applications
inner systems iris data platform
ready set code
visit intersystems.com try iris to learn
more
can you talk about the components that
make up a k-sql db system with respect
to
how it works in an existing kafka
deployment and how it fits in
yeah absolutely so you know in a
traditional database architecture
you have kind of commit log and then you
have these tables
uh that have your data represented in
different ways effectively this looks
a lot like that except that the commit
log is now kafka
and the the tables are are actually
materialized
in the k-sql db cluster so in k-sql db
you would have a set of nodes
those nodes you know read and write
streams of data from kafka they may
materialize it into
rock cb which is not actually kind of a
full database in the sense of having you
know sql and supporting remote access
it's an embedded key value store that
just maintains the data format on disk
and so that's that's how the
kind of indexes and tables are stored to
allow lookups
and so so that that's how it works and
you know this makes
case equal to be kind of elastically
scalable you can add
new nodes and they will take over part
of the work
of query processing uh automatically so
you can kind of scale it out
or or scale it down elastically by by
adding or removing nodes from that
cluster
and it you know it it works similar to
kafka
itself where there's a kind of
partitioned workload so you can imagine
taking one of these tables and
chopping it up into little pieces and
storing those pieces
spread across the cluster and you can do
that with some replication so that
you know if one of the nodes fails it it
doesn't uh go away
but the the kind of long-term store for
all data is
is in kafka itself the roc cb instance
is really just kind of a cache and so
even if it's replicated
you know it is just kind of a quick look
up index not the kind of authoritative
source if that makes sense
so if you were to lose the instance of
rocksdb you could rebuild that data from
your kafka topics is that yeah that's
exactly right so
so and it's common with stream
processing you may calculate
a bunch of things and they want to
recalculate them later and you may you
may indeed want to throw away all your
data and kind of start over
and and reprocess from the beginning as
a simplistic way of getting there
so that's you know that's kind of the
basic architecture
all the actual processing and
computation happens
in the k sequel db nodes you know kafka
is just
being kafka it's it's reading and
writing the streams and replicating them
and storing them
so it's not it's not the case that these
queries are kind of going off to the
kafka cluster and doing anything like
that one of the things we felt was very
important was
making sure that kafka itself works
really well as a multi-tenant
system that can be shared across many
teams and use cases without tipping over
whereas k-sql db you can do all kinds of
complicated munging
and you can have many k-sql db clusters
that feed off the same kafka cluster
they can all share data
but they don't you know interfere with
each other if you do some kind of very
abusive
query processing in your k-sql db
instances it won't
it won't hurt your uh co-workers and
i think that's an important pro property
for any of these things that
go across teams is to to think through
how that
you know multi-tenancy architecture is
meant to work and so
for us it's you know kafka is the shared
part and it does
very simple predictable things k sequel
does all the complicated stuff but is
meant to be
you know clusters that are not really
shared across
uh teams and meant to be multi-tenant
instead you would give each
tenant their own capacity and it's
actually a very flexible model
you know typically in databases if i
give you your own database you don't
have access to my data
but because of this shared commit log at
the center everybody has access to the
same stuff
it's just a question of how you index it
and process it in different
in different clusters speaking of
indexes relational databases tend to
have certain indexes can you create
additional indexes on top of
your massaged data that you're consuming
from
kafka topics and ingesting it to k sql
db can you have indexes on top of that
for faster lookups and
all of that yeah so we don't support
kind of secondary indexes yet but you
can of course just materialize the data
in different ways which which
effectively serves the same purpose
and is maybe more in the style of this
kind of stream processing
we'll probably add secondary indexes
just to make the pull queries
simpler in certain cases and and have
less materialized data but there hasn't
been a big push for it yet
so k sequel db sort of simplifies
how you can access the data uh case
streams or the stream api on top of
kafka let you
do the same thing so what's the
correspondence between the two can you
do everything that you can do with
streams with case sequel
and vice versa yeah i would say you can
do the vast majority obviously
with an open api that supports code
you can do more than than you could do
in sql
so the the relationship is this actually
the streams api is a lower level set of
kind of java primitives for doing stream
processing operations
joins aggregations filtering
you know all the things you might
imagine doing with data you know
it looks like one of these you know kind
of fluent apis where you chain together
a bunch of operations one after the
other if you you know if you've used
java the the kind of streams interface
in java is similar to this where you
would you know change
maps and uh reduces and and aggregates
and and so it works like that except it
does this on
these infinite streams not just finite
collections and and does it in a
persistent
and partitioned and distributed and
fault tolerant way so that's what the
stream's
api and kafka provides case sequel db is
actually built on top of that
so it uses those primitives under the
covers but it does do more than that so
it
it provides a sql layer on top of that
it also it provides remote access
so that you can run these kind of pull
queries you can you know send
new queries to it and then it also
controls the connect api
in kafka so you can run uh
and it brings both of those together and
so we feel like that really broadens the
appeal
you know maybe java has whatever you
want to call it
40 of the programmer market but but kind
of everybody knows sql
and it's also just a lot less work to
put together a sql query than it is to
kind of build and test a full
java application so it's not really you
know
depending on the use case it's not that
one exactly replaces the other
you know for for building kind of a very
complicated
custom set of business logic there's a
good chance you're still going to do
that in java
but for a lot of simple data
transformations
materializing caches of data you know
looking for the bad patterns for
security that's the kind of thing where
you just want to
write the query just say what you mean
not not write a ton of code and compile
it and deploy it and all that kind of
stuff
and that's that's really where k sql dp
shines is those
those kind of simple streaming use cases
so there seems to be like a trade-off
between
ease of use versus expressiveness of
what you want to do
for expressivity just use like case
streams and otherwise use case equal
i think that's exactly right you know
you could you could think of there being
kind of a hierarchy here where
the lowest level producer and consumer
apis that write streams
they kind of have all the power you know
they in kafka they have the
transactional processing
in theory if you're willing to write
enough code you can do everything with
that
but that's a lot of code in most cases
and you would end up rewriting the same
stuff over and over again and that's
where these
the kind of connector api and streams
api provide the next
layer up in that stack it's a little bit
higher of an abstraction it makes it
easier to get
you know correct results and reason
about what happens if the machine fails
in the middle of processing something
but you do trade off you know a little
bit of flexibility in in how you
how you write that versus the low level
read and write and then one level up
from that
i think is is k sqldb so the analogy you
can use is
you know if you've ever used one of
these key value interfaces
like roxdb itself you know it's kind of
very flexible and allowing you to work
with data at a low level
probably more so than a sql interface
but it's actually a lot more work for
kind of simple stuff
that you might want to do than using a
sql database is there
a notion of transactions within k-sql db
can i ingest a particular set of events
only if a certain condition is satisfied
is there um you know an all-or-nothing
sort of a guarantee and
traditional you know what relation
databases have yeah there is although
it's a little bit different so so since
the domain
is stream processing and and the pull
cores are mostly for looking up
results it's really about how can you
guarantee the correctness
of that processing so and you can
imagine a lot of corner cases here so
you know what if you know a message was
delivered and processed
and then the you know the the stream
processing application died
and then it kind of came back and it
gets that message again
you know what happens so in my census
example where i was kind of counting
uh births and deaths you wanna you don't
to double count a birth right
and end up with the wrong the wrong
number of
people in a given city and there's a lot
of corner cases like that that you could
imagine
and you know it's very similar actually
to the domain of
transactions in normal databases and the
underlying kafka apis support
a transactional concept and and so it
works just like you would imagine a
transaction you say begin
you do a bunch of writes and then you
say commit
and then all of those rights either
happen together or they don't
they don't happen at all and so the the
stream processing functionality in in
case equal to b uses that
so it says okay you know i'm working
across these different topics and so on
i need to make sure that
whatever happens network glitches the
you know one of the nodes fails
uh i still get the you know the correct
output
in this case correct output means the
same output i would have gotten if
nothing had gone wrong
right and people often refer to this as
exactly once semantics meaning you get
the same
semantics as if the message had been
delivered just one time even though of
course
under the hood you may send some message
over network you don't know if it got
there
the thing fails it comes back it gets it
again you know under the hood many
things are happening
you want to get the the uh the same
output you would as if everything worked
perfectly
and so that's that's uh supported within
k sql db
and it's it's an important thing to to
be able to have that you know
there have been a whole history of uh
stream processing layers
over the last you know five plus years
and they've kind of built up
functionality that makes it easier and
easier to use and so on
a lot of the early ones didn't really
have any um real guarantees in this area
and or they had very weak guarantees
of course that makes it very very hard
to write any kind of important
application on top of it if you can't
guarantee that you get the right output
then it's only really usable for things
where the the answer doesn't matter
and and so you know that kind of
guarantee is very important it is end to
end
because you have to reason about what's
in kafka
you know k sql db's part how it gets out
into the other systems that it might
ultimately end up in as a destination
and so that that is another
part of the simplicity i think you can
bring in this area by having a bunch of
components that are built to work
together
on the query side of things can you join
different tables uh different kafka
topics to get a
result that you want yeah absolutely and
the the use case for that
in a in stream processing it isn't
always obvious to people
but um there's actually quite a lot of
that so one of the examples i gave was
you know you have this stream of sales
but the sale
in it it probably just has your like
customer id right
but a lot of what you would need to do
to process a sale
in different ways you probably need a
bunch of other information about the
customer maybe you need their
primary shipping address or whatever the
case may be your you probably need to
join on that information
and so so you can imagine the
sale as being a you know stream of
events you could imagine the customer
information as being a kind of table
you're joining that stream and table
together and
so you know it supports all the
combinations here you can join a stream
to a stream
so in advertising you have clicks and
you have impressions
and one of the problems is often trying
to say hey which uh
impression which which viewing of the ad
led to the click on the ad that's a kind
of stream
join the stream to a stream right in
normal databases of course you join
tables
uh there's a lot of that you might have
streams you might have streams coming
out of different
databases where you're kind of capturing
the feed of changes
and you might want to aggregate all that
so a common example of this is where
you have bits of data about your
customer
spread over many different systems in a
company any big company ends up with
this problem where you're like hey we
we know a lot about our customers but
you have to go to 27 systems to
figure out the answer and you know
that's an example where
if you treat the changes coming into
each of those records
in each of those systems as a as a kind
of
change log then with kafka connect you
can kind of extract that from those
systems
and you have this feed and then using k
sql db you can effectively
you know produce this kind of streaming
join that gives you the
you know the end-all be-all you know
record for each customer that has all
the information together
and so that's that's an example of a
normal kind of table
table to table join so all these
combinations of streams and tables
are actually pretty useful in this
domain once you start to think about it
you mentioned earlier that it's possible
to have multiple k-sequel db instances
maintaining their own table or
connection that can come and go
so from a client perspective can i join
on data that's on two different k sequel
db
nodes is it there's a is there a
distributed query of sorts or is it
isolated to a single source
yeah yeah so that's true both in two
different ways so
you know a k sql db cluster is made out
of multiple nodes
and then you can have many clusters uh
working off of the same kafka cluster
and so so i was actually saying both
things so so you could have
you know i could have my cluster you
could have your cluster and then within
my cluster it's actually spread over
multiple nodes
so the the data itself is partitioned up
and of course you
um you would need to be able to join
across
different partitions the actual join
itself is performed locally so it would
reshuffle the data to get it into the
same node to do the join it's not doing
like a remote rpc call for each lookup
so you know under the under the hood it
would be done locally
but yeah you can join uh you know
different different topics together in
different ways
so since you're using roxdb as a backing
storage layer can you
use roxdb in conjunction with k sqldb as
a traditional
relational database create a classic
table on rocksdb and then use the two
things to sort of query
ingest etc yeah i mean rocksdb itself
the the db in the name maybe oversells
what it is to people
you know it is just kind of a put get
scan
uh interface in c and java so it doesn't
support any sql or anything like that
so that you know the table concept is of
course using that under the hood to
store these partitions of data in k-sql
db
and you can combine the tables and
streams in k-sql db
but there's not really a sql interface
to to
you know directly access the rox db part
other than the the k-sql interface
itself
but i think probably the use case you
would want to use that for you actually
can do in k-sql db itself
so you did mention that k-sql db has a
schema
of sorts where you can declare you know
columns and a primary key
and you're consuming from kafka topics
so how do you deal with
changes in screamer schema from your
upstream sub publishers of data yeah
that's that's a great question
so yeah i guess like any uh sql layer
okay sql db it needs it needs a notion
of what the data is
and that lets it get into the records
and munch on them in a smart way
so you know you can you can kind of
express that just yourself by saying hey
i assert this is what's in this data
feed maybe you know maybe of json
records and you're saying i'm
i'm saying it's going to have these four
fields and that's the
scheme of my table obviously if somebody
upstream publishes mangled
json then you got a problem so it does
also support
usage with what we would call a schema
registry so so confluent
produces something that maintains these
schemas along with kafka
and that's a way it's actually a very
important component for the usage of
kafka i talked about the usage of kafka
across
different teams obviously that only
works if we all understand each other's
bytes
which means we have to agree on the
format and so this this allows you to
maintain the format of data
in common formats so protocol buffers or
abro or json
it'll store a schema for that it'll
check the data against that
and then you can express different
compatibility rules
so you may have some kafka topics where
you say hey it's wild west
put whatever you want in and good luck
to whoever's downstream
the reality is for important data if you
have a lot of applications building
around it
you don't want to be in a situation
where the person putting data in or
the many teams putting people data in
have to go talk to all the teams
downstream
it just gets really hard to
organizationally maintain correctness in
that world
so so typically in those situations you
would enforce
uh some notion of forwards or backwards
compatibility
you know which which control what you're
allowed to do
right so the most restrictive would be
you can't change it at all
the reality is in in most businesses
the problem changes over time you know
the the software needs to evolve
so that's usually too restrictive so but
you usually do want to have some notion
of compatibility around
you know okay you can add fields but you
can't
you know change the type on an existing
field because that's going to break
downstream code it's going to break case
equal you know db whatever whatever is
relying on the format of that so you
would want to use that schema registry
to enforce these requirements
and that's actually quite common this is
a very popular
uh open component that that we produce
that you know is very commonly used with
with kafka itself
since you have a cluster of k sql db
nodes
i can presumably write a query in
different ways
if i go to a relational database and
write a query there's ways to sort of
understand what the cost of the query is
plan and kind of get some feedback about
it could be written in a different way
for faster access so in the presence of
this cluster of k-sequel db nodes that
are maintaining their own tables and
views
is there some assisting for query
planning
optimization and all of that yeah um you
know we have a little bit of
functionality to to let you understand
what's going on under the hood it's it's
not as mature
i think as the more mature databases and
what they provide
you know some of that is because the
the pull queries themselves are actually
simpler in terms of what we support so
there's less to debug there
what you actually need in addition to
that is is you know the ability to
really change
and evolve queries in a way you wouldn't
in a relational database right because
if you have a query that just happens
for a point in time and then is done
then you don't really need to evolve it
in place but with stream processing you
have these queries that might run
forever right so if i'm computing you
know how many sales happened in each
city
at some point my logic for how i count
that or how i define cities might change
and so so in addition to the kind of
explained plan stuff
what you also need is the ability to go
back and reprocess data and that's
something we've put some thought into
there's kind of ongoing work to help
with that kind of query evolution make
it easier to do that in place without
having to go back and reprocess data
so that's that's kind of an interesting
nuance as well and when it comes to
actually accessing your data
since you have a cluster is there a way
to find the table or do you need to know
exactly where that node is its ip
address or
a dns lookup name or whatever yeah the
um the interaction with k sql db is very
very similar to
most of the relational databases so if
you've used mysql or postgres or oracle
you know you there's a little command
line shell that you can hook up with
uh there's a rest api but on the command
line shell you can do exactly what you
would expect which is
you know show me the table show me the
streams i want to do this you can kind
of interactively develop these queries
see what the results of different things
would be you know run these queries
you can manage some of the background
queries like kill the
you know kill the long-running ones so
you know it's very similar to those
systems and what it provides
do you have any comments on performance
of k-sequel db and how quickly you can
ingest things
um in comparison with say a relational
database what's stopping or
why use k-sql db or say a relational
database that could be ingesting
the same amount of data every event that
comes in
yeah yeah that's a great question so so
so yeah you know if
if what you're building is ultimately
you know a ui driven app
where there's a pile of data that kind
of sits there and you just
do lookups to show the result then i
think that
you know that's that's effectively what
a relational database is built to do
and they do it pretty well and there's
different you know there's 101 databases
probably one that's a good fit
for whatever the application you're
building is and i don't know that
there's really a motivation to adopt
anything new
this other side of things around stream
processing
you know that's something that databases
don't do at all uh and so you want
you end up pushed into this world where
you're you know
liking the data as well you dump a bunch
of data in
and then at the end of the day you run
some big batch computation to get it
into shape
so everything's like a day old and you
know that's that's nowhere right in the
modern world
that's that's where stream processing
shines so i would say the you know the
goal
of adopting this is not so much that
postgres wasn't fast enough
it's actually that you know the the
application you're building is actually
a
stream processing application you're
reacting to things as they occur
and you know there's a lot of use cases
that just require that
that kind of access pattern so then um
you know
how does the performance compare yeah
it's hard to compare because they don't
you know these other systems don't do
stream processing so
you know the k sql db just does
relatively simple lookups
so so the typical like you know if you
if you ran it through one of these
data data warehouse uh quarry benchmarks
that like you couldn't do most of
queries in that it just does some simple
lookups right on the pull query side
so the pull queries are fast but not
nearly as expressive yet
that's an area we're adding and then of
course the stream processing doesn't
exist at all
in those those other systems so so it's
probably hard to do apples to apples
comparison
in terms of raw performance of you know
how how what can you use this on
you know there's there's kind of a poor
node number
which is actually quite good you can you
can process you know
hundreds of thousands of records per
second on one node
but but like a lot of these modern
systems it's a proper distributed system
and it scales
horizontally so you could add you know
if you want more then you just add more
machines
uh and you can do that uh dynamically as
it runs so as you know as the query is
processing you can add more
uh capacity to make it go faster so so
we
you know we've run on workloads that are
actually massive in scale where it's you
know
millions of uh records per second that's
great
so in kafka you could have older events
sort of expiring or falling off of the
topic so how does that flow back into k
sqldb
let's say i have some expiration that
says just forget about
events from 30 days ago for compliance
or whatever
how does that flow into your k sql db
instance in terms of the aggregates
you're computing
or the transformations that you've done
on top of the underlying data
yeah you're saying maybe we can start
that one over i'm not sure if i
understood the question so you're saying
like the compliance of the data or the
retention
uh so retention let's let's say
retention of data and topics you can
configure that right so
um since you have these push queries or
pull queries
and do you actually see data twice when
things sort of
are deleted because of retention
policies yeah that's a that's a great
question so
you know in a stream you would have this
idea of maintaining
you know data just for some period of
time in theory that period of time could
be forever
but if that's the case you're going to
need more storage over time as more data
accumulates
in a table it works just like a database
does so
you know the table data is stored
forever so if you have your customer
accounts the assumption is
you you wouldn't ever you know time out
you know your customer account that
would stay forever
uh under the hood we do actually support
kind of a time modeled table
that's important for some of the
windowing concepts you know as you
compute
aggregates over a window like how many
uh people were born in last however many
days
but the at least in the common case you
could think of tables as being just like
a database table where
it persists until you delete it so
internally was there any reason you
chose rocksdb what was uh
what was the motivation behind that yeah
um you know
effectively we're using you know just
kind of a
some persistent key value interface and
so it doesn't particularly matter
what that key value interface is and so
there's there's a set of these different
embeddables key value interfaces that
run as libraries
it would be overkill to have something
that had like a sql layer
of its own or a bunch of advanced
database features it literally is just a
library that we use for maintaining data
on disk
and uh all the distributed systems
replication of data
sql processing that's all done uh by k
sql db itself so
so yeah then when you look at different
libraries they all have pluses and
minuses
um technically it's actually pluggable
within
kafka streams which is is used for these
underlying primitives
and so you can actually plug in anything
you want there's a there's a all in
memory version of it
it could have some advantages and
there's other systems out there you
could adopt but
most people use rocks to be it's it's um
you know there's pros and cons it's
i think extremely uh featureful and
um very high performance you know the
con is it has about a million tuning
knobs
so uh there you know there's uh if you
don't like the performance
you can almost certainly fix it if you
can discover the right the right tuning
um
so operationally how is this packaged
along with kafka do i need to manage a
separate rocks db
instance tune it and all of that or is
it just out of the box it's available
no no so so um you know i think you you
guys did a
a podcast on cockroachdb they they use
it as well right so for for both of us
the word db and rock cb is maybe a
misnomer
it is actually just a library and it
accesses the local disk
and so it's uh you know it's really just
a library that
that maintains a certain file format on
disk it uh
it's not something you would install
separately it's not something that's
accessed remotely over a network
it's not something that has a sql
interface so
you know anything which accesses data on
disk you have to pay a little more
attention to
but but yeah there's no operational
component of it effectively
you start this k sql db process
and it has everything it it needs you
know what you have to tell k sql db is
where's kafka
and um you know that's that's really the
the
the things you have to have is is kafka
and are there any anti-patterns
of using k-sql db for stream processing
such as building a
push-based application for example using
kafka stream api versus k-sql db
are there anti-patterns of using one
over the other where it's not compatible
yeah probably the probably the biggest
anti-pattern in stream processing i
think
is you know trying to do
remote lookups for every record and so
this is kind of a very natural thing in
software
where you know if you have one thing and
you want to look up the corresponding
record you do some remote call
to get that corresponding record so in
the example i gave
i had the sale i want to look up the
customer record
there's a tendency for engineers to want
to you know take each thing and do a
remote call on the other thing
and it usually just isn't the easiest
most correct or most performant way to
do that because you have to reason about
what happens if that call fails and how
do i retry it and all this stuff so the
more natural
way of doing that in case equal db would
be to capture
the stream of changes on the customer
data and capture the stream of sales
and then do that join within k-sql
rather than trying to do it in the
application
space itself that will that will kind of
have the right properties around
reasoning about time it'll have the
right fault tolerance properties
and it'll be a lot faster because you're
not kind of doing a remote call on each
item with all the kind of latency and
whatever that that implies
so that's probably the biggest
anti-pattern that people miss
which is just a little different from
how people use traditional databases
where you're often joining
you're doing joins kind of in your code
over the network between different
things and it works better because
you're
you're typically just doing that for one
or two rows whereas in stream processing
there's a whole feed of these
especially when you go to re-run your
processing if you change your logic you
want it
to work quickly so you can get back
caught up to the current time
so what's the future of k-sql db where
is it going
yeah um well well you know our goal is
to really make
working with streams of events as easy
as possible
so and and that's really our vision at
confluent
kind of end to end and so there's
there's a lot of work to try and make
that easy like we're you know we're
building all this as a cloud service to
try and make the operation side of it go
away
it's you know making all the features
available that just make it really easy
to work with this and make it easy to
work across a large company
so in case you could be the the parts of
that that are important i mentioned just
completing
the set of functionality that people
want in pull queries
that's a ton of work because it's like
all the stuff databases do so we got
you know long red map of things to fill
out that side of things
you know we're still not trying to
replace traditional databases for
you know what they're good at like
building kind of end-to-end ui driven
apps but we want to make these
you know event stream processing
architectures really simple and make the
access to that data really easy
in an integrated system there's work
going on around
making it really easy to test and evolve
these queries the kind of full life
cycle
of development for it and then a ton of
work on just
the the full completeness of all the
processing capabilities performance all
the operational side of it so
you know lots going on uh i guess
whenever you're trying to build a
database it's it's a lot of work
so so we're not running out of things to
do so is k sequel db open source
yeah it's available under the community
license that confluent uses
and so um it's not an osi open source
license but you can take it you can
modify the code you don't have to pass
anything
you know you can make changes to it and
publish those
the only major restrictions around how
that can be run
as part of uh kind of managed sas cloud
service
which you know that right is reserved
all the details are in the the license
itself
but that's that's the same license that
we produce our schema registry and other
components under and it's it's very
popular and
you know gets a lot of free usage and of
course you can do exactly what you'd
expect which is
go look at it all in github and make
your own fork with that
awesome so is there anything else that
you want to add about k sql db
uh no i i think it's you know if you're
interested in in databases and data
systems i
i think this world of events and event
streaming is
is really becoming a big deal you know
it's kind of becoming part of the modern
stack and
i think it's a great tool to make
working with this really easy and
productive
so i'd urge people to go check it out
and give it a spin
you know you can try it out pretty
easily and there's a pretty active
community around it so
you know if you kick the tires and there
there's something that doesn't make
sense or it doesn't work the way you
expect let us know
um there's a set of people contributing
patches and a bunch of people at
confluent working on it actively so we'd
love to hear feedback from people
i'll include some notes in the show
notes on how people can try k sql db
with that j uh thanks for being here to
talk about k-sequel db
this is akshay manchali for software
engineering radio thank you for
listening
thanks so much for having me inner
systems iris is the fastest way to build
applications
so take advantage of that extra time on
your hands and use it to learn a new
data platform
deliver complex mission critical
applications on the fastest route
possible
with data from any source embedded
analytics and interactive user
interfaces
with inner systems iris you can connect
your systems
use any data model and apply machine
learning
now's the time to level up your database
platform and try out inner systems iris
so you can collaborate build and deploy
faster than ever before
don't wait any longer level up your
skills with inner systems iris
ready set code
visit intersystems.com try iris to learn
more
thanks for listening to sc radio an
educational program brought to you by
ieee software magazine
for more about the podcast including
other episodes visit our website at
se radio.net to provide feedback you can
comment on each episode
on the website or reach us on linkedin
facebook
twitter or through our slack channel at
scradio.slack.com
you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of se radio
is licensed under creative commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening